Robert Franklin Gates
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Robert Franklin Gates papers
1910-1988, bulk 1928-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Gates, Robert Franklin
2.3 linear feet
The papers of Washington, D.C. area painter and art instructor Robert Franklin Gates date from 1910-1988, bulk 1928-1988, and measure 2.3 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials; letters from government agencies, museums, galleries, and colleagues; business records primarily concerning transactions with the Jack Rasmussen Gallery; artwork including scattered drawings by Gates and block prints by Joe Goethe and D. Neufeld; two scrapbooks; printed materials; and photographs of Gates, family members, models, artwork, and exhibition installations. There are also photograph albums and miscellaneous photographs documenting a 1936 voyage to the Virgin Islands commissioned by the U.S. Treasury Department.
Provenance
The Robert Franklin Gates papers were donated in 1995 by Sarita W. Gates, the artist's widow, via legal representative Bradford G. Weekes III.
Related Material
Also in the Archives of American Art are the papers of Gates' first wife Margaret Casey Gates, 1934-1988,
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Robert Franklin Gates was born on October 6, 1906 in Detroit, Michigan. He studied at the Detroit School of Arts and Crafts, and from 1929 to 1930 attended the Art Students' League in New York. Between 1930 and 1932, Gates studied under C. Law Watkins at the Phillips Gallery Art School in Washington, D.C., later becoming an instructor in life drawing and painting there. During this time, he met fellow student Margaret Casey, and they married on January 7, 1933. Between 1934 and 1938, Robert Gates was an art instructor at the Studio House in Washington, D.C.
In 1934, Gates received a commission from the U.S. Treasury Department Section of Fine Arts to create a series of watercolors of Charles Gardens, South Carolina, and from 1929-1940, murals for post offices in Bethesda, Maryland, Oakland, Maryland, and Lewisburg, West Virginia. In 1936, the Treasury Department also commissioned Gates and fellow artists Mitchell Jamieson and Prentiss Taylor to create series of watercolors of the Virgin Islands, arranging for several voyages there.
Between 1937 and 1942, Gates was a guest instructor at the University of Florida, taught art classes at Hood College in Frederick, Maryland and at the Washington County Museum of Art in Hagerstown, Maryland. He also taught at the Phillips Gallery Art School in Washington, D.C. while his wife was employed as the school secretary. In 1938, Gates received a summer scholarship to study under Henry Varnum Poor at the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center.
During World War II, Gates worked as a civilian technician for the Navy Department doing model making and camouflage design, receiving the Distinguished Civilian Service Award for his work.
After the war, and the closing of the Phillips Gallery Art School, Gates attended classes taught by Bill Calfee at American University. In 1946, he joined the faculty and eventually becane chairman of the Art Department in 1954. Robert and Margaret Gates were divorced sometime in the mid-1950s. From 1966 to 1967, Gates was Artist-in-Residence at the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad, Iraq, under the Department of State Educational and Cultural Exchange Program. In 1967, he married his second wife, Sarita, while in Baghdad.
Gates is represented in the permanent collections of the American University, the Baltimore Museum of Art, the Corcoran Gallery of Art, the Dumbarton Oaks collection, the Phillips Collection, and the Lewisshon collection.
Robert Franklin Gates died on March 11, 1982 in Alexandria, Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Washington, D.C. area painter and art instructor Robert Franklin Gates date from 1910-1988, bulk 1928-1988, and measure 2.3 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical materials; letters from government agencies, museums, galleries, and colleagues; business records primarily concerning transactions with the Jack Rasmussen Gallery; artwork including scattered drawings by Gates and block prints by Joe Goethe and D. Neufeld; two scrapbooks; printed materials; and photographs of Gates, family members, models, artwork, and exhibition installations. There are also photograph albums and miscellaneous photographs documenting a 1936 voyage to the Virgin Islands commissioned by the U.S. Treasury Department.
Biographical material includes resumes, biographical accounts, award certificates, records for employment through a State Department Specialists Grant, address lists, teaching notes, writings about Gates, and a guest book signed by colleagues celebrating Gates' forty years at American University. There is a also a group of Navy Department records documenting Gates' employment designing three-dimensional photo-surfaced topography models for use by troops during World War II.
Letters are primarily from the U.S. Treasury Department and the Federal Works Agency discussing commissions, including the painting of post office murals in Maryland and West Virginia, and from various museums and galleries discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities. There are one or two letters each from colleagues Alice Acheson, Adelyn Breeskin, Charles Burchfield, Alida Conover, John Gernand, Duncan Phillips, Henry Varnum Poor, and Prentiss Taylor. Some letters are Christmas cards decorated with original block prints.
Business records primarily document Gates' interaction with the Jack Rasmussen Gallery in Washington, D.C., but also include miscellaneous sales records and pay stubs from American University.
Artwork consists of scattered drawings of modern houses by Gates and abstract sketches by others, and small block prints by Joe Goethe and D. Neufeld. Two Scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scattered letters.
Additional printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Gates and others, prospectuses for art exhibitions, press releases, calendars of events, booklets about color and lenses, brochures for art schools and books, and an unannotated calendar containing a reproduction of one of Gates' paintings.
Photographs are of Robert Gates, various family members including Gates with his first wife photographed by Prentiss Taylor, models, artwork, and exhibition installations. There are two photograph albums and unbound photographs documenting a 1936 voyage to the Virgin Islands commissioned by the U.S. Treasury Department. Images of this trip are of Gates and colleagues including Mitchell Jamieson, the ship Doris Hamlin, the crew, markets, a cock fight, miscellaneous buildings, town squares, and the countryside of the Virgin Islands.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series. Each series is arranged chronologically:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1928-1975 (Box 1, OV 4; 34 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1930-1988 (Box 1; 25 folders)
Series 3: Business Records, 1961-1982 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, circa 1962 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1932-1939 (Box 1-2; 4 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1916-1988 (Box 2; 48 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1910-1982 (Boxes 2-3, OV 4; 20 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed under the following terms:
Subjects:
American University (Washington, D.C.)Fine Arts Dept -- Faculty; United States -- Dept. of the Treasury -- Section of Fine Arts; Jack Rasmussen Gallery (Washington, D.C.)
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- Washington (D.C.); Mural painting and decoration, American; Art teachers -- Washington (D.C.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; Post office buildings
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Drawings; Christmas cards; Scrapbooks
Names:
Taylor, Prentiss, 1907-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1928-1975, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 4; 34 folders)
  Biographical material includes resumes, biographical accounts, award certificates, and Navy Department employment records which include letters, writings, floor plan drawings, and photographs concerning Gates's designs for three-dimensional photo-surfaced topography models during World War II. Also included are records of employment through a State Department Specialists Grant, address lists, teaching notes, writings about Gates, and a guest book signed by colleagues celebrating Gate's forty years at American University.
  - Student Pilot Permit, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resumes and Biographical Accounts, 1957-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Award Certificates, 1933-1975, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Navy Department Employment Records, 1942-1951, (20 folders; oversized items housed in OV 4) (Box 1, Folder 5-24)
  - State Department Specialists Grant Employment Records, 1966-1967, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Address Lists, 1956, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - Teaching Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Writings about Robert Gates, 1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Guest Book for Roberts Gates "Gala," 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Nine Oversize Drawings of Floor Plans for the Photo-Surfaced Model Project from the Navy Department Employment Records, 1945, (removed from Box 1, F 5-24) (Box OV 4)
- Letters, 1930-1988, Series 2:; (Box 1; 25 folders)
  Letters are from the U.S. Treasury Department and the Federal Works Agency regarding commissions, and from various museums and galleries discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities. There are one or two letters each from colleagues Alice Acheson, Adelyn Breeskin, Charles Burchfield, Alida Conover, John Gernand, Duncan Phillips, Henry Varnum Poor, and Prentiss Taylor. Some letters are Christmas cards decorated with original block prints.
  - Letters from Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "A-G," undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "H-Z," undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letters, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Letters, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letters, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Letters, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Letters, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Letters, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Letters, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Letters, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Letters, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letters, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letters, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Letters, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Letters, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Letters, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letters, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Letters, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Letters, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Business Records, 1961-1982, Series 3:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  This series consists primarily of business transactions with the Jack Rasmussen Gallery in Washington, D.C. Also included are miscellaneous sales records and pay stubs from American University.
  - Records Concerning the Jack Rasmussen Gallery, 1975-1982, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 59-61)
  - Miscellaneous Sales Records, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Pay Stubs from American University, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Artwork, circa 1962, Series 4:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  Artwork consists of scattered drawings by Gates, including images of Bauhaus style houses. There are also block prints by Joe Goethe and D. Neufeld.
  - Drawings by Robert Gates, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Drawings by an Unidentified Artist, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Block Prints by Joe Goethe, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 66-68)
  - Block Print by D. Neufeld, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Scrapbooks, 1932-1939, Series 5:; (Box 1, 2; 4 folders)
  Two scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scattered letters documenting the beginning of Gates's career. One scrapbook has been disbound.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1933-1939, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Printed Material, 1916-1988, Series 6:; (Box 2; 48 folders)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, prospectuses for art exhibitions, press releases, calendars of events, booklets about color and lenses, brochures for art schools and books, and an unannotated calendar containing a reproduction of one of Gates's paintings.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1916-1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1936, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Clippings, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1931-1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1947-1982 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Prospectuses for Art Exhibitions, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Press Releases, 1941-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Calendars of Events, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Booklets Concerning Color, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Booklet Concerning Lenses, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Brochures for Schools, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Brochure for Books, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Unannotated Calendar Containing a Reproduction of a Painting by Robert Gates, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Photographs, circa 1910-1982, Series 7:; (Boxes 2-3, OV 4; 20 folders)
  Photographs are of Robert Gates, various family members, models, artwork, and exhibition installations. There are also two photograph albums and miscellaneous photographs documenting a 1936 voyage to the Virgin Islands commissioned by the U.S. Treasury Department that include images of Gates and colleagues including Mitchell Jamieson, the ship Doris Hamlin, the crew, markets, a cock fight, miscellaneous buildings, town squares, and the countryside of the Virgin Islands.
  - Photographs of Robert Gates, circa 1910-1982, (2 folders; oversized items housed in OV 4) (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
  - Photographs by Sam Tamashiro of Robert Gates Conducting Class, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
  - Photographs of Family Members, 1934-1967, undated, (oversized items housed in OV 4) (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Photographs by Prentiss Taylor of Robert Gates and Margaret Casey Gates in Charleston, South Carolina, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Album 1 of Photographs of Voyage to the Virgin Islands, 1936 (Box 3 (pam), Folder 1)
  - Album 2 of Photographs of Voyage to the Virgin Islands, 1936 (Box 3 (pam), Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Voyage to the Virgin Islands, 1936, (5 folders) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 3-7)
  - Photographs of Nude Models, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Robert Gates, 1939-1972, undated, (oversized items housed in OV 4) (Box 3 (pam), Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, 1940, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3 (pam), Folder 13)
  - Three Oversize Photographs of Robert Gates, undated, (separated from Box 2, F52-53) (Box OV 4)
  - Oversize Photograph of a Member of Robert Gates' Family, undated, (separated from Box 2, F54-55) (Box OV 4)
  - Oversize Photograph of Post Office Mural, Bethesda, Maryland, 1939, (separated from Box 3, F10) (Box OV 4)